A Finding Aid to the Poindexter Gallery Records, 1931-1985, bulk 1955-1978, in the Archives of American Art AAA.poingall
Archives of American Art
Poindexter Gallery records
bulk 1955-1978
1931-1985
AAA.poingall
Archives of American Art
6.8 Linear feet
The records of the Poindexter Gallery measure 6.8 linear feet and date from 1931-1985 with the bulk of the materials dating from 1955-1978 when the gallery was active. The majority of the collection consists of artists’ files documenting the gallery’s relationships with its artists, including exhibitions, and containing a wide variety of materials, including photographs. Also found are the "desk files" kept by the gallery’s founder, Elinor Poindexter; correspondence; and financial and legal records.
Poindexter Gallery
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Elinor Poindexter Desk Files, 1947-1969 (Box 1, 8 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1955-1971 (Box 1-2, 1.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Artists’ Files, 1931-1983, undated (Box 2-5, 2.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Financial and Legal Files, 1955-1985 (Box 5-6, 1.0 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographic Materials, 1933-1977 (Box 6-7, 1.4 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
The Poindexter Gallery was founded in 1955 in New York City by Elinor Poindexter. The gallery specialized in sculpture, abstract, and figurative art and featured the works of such artists as Richard Diebenkorn, Jules Olitski, Nell Blaine, William de Kooning, Giorgio Spaventa, Franz Kline, Earl Kerkam, Milton Resnick and Robert De Niro, among others. The Poindexter Gallery closed in 1978.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Poindexter Gallery records were donated over a period from 1968-1978 by the Poindexter Gallery via owners Elinor Poindexter and art director Harold Fondren. A 2006 accession was donated by Christie Poindexter Dennis, daughter of Elinor.
Related Archival Materials note
Among other resources relating to the Poindexter Gallery records in the Archives of American Art is an oral history with gallery owner, Elinor Poindexter, conducted by Paul Cummings on September 9, 1970.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Poindexter Gallery measure 6.8 linear feet and date from 1931-1985 with the bulk of the materials dating from 1955-1978 when the gallery was active. The majority of the collection consists of artists’ files documenting the gallery’s relationships with its artists, including exhibitions, and containing a wide variety of materials, including photographs. Also found are the "desk files" kept by the gallery’s founder, Elinor Poindexter; correspondence; and financial and legal records.
Elinor Poindexter's desk files consist of documents she kept as a reference for both her personal needs and gallery business. Correspondence is with artists, museums, colleges and universities, and art institutes. Notable correspondents include Worcester Art Museum, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Solomon Guggenheim Museum, Denver Art Museum, Yale University, Oberlin College, University of Arizona, the Fogg Art Museum at Harvard University, Smithsonian Institution, and the Montana Historical Association. Additional correspondence is found throughout desk files and artists’ files as well.
Artists’ files are found for artists represented by the gallery, or in whom the gallery took an interest. Contents of the files vary, but may contain correspondence, photographs, sales records, exhibition files, and printed materials. There is extensive material relating to artists Richard Diebenkorn, William de Kooning, Giorgio Spaventa, Robert De Niro, Earl Kerkam, Franz Kline, Milton Resnick, Eleanor Dickinson, Paul Harris, Jules Olitski, among others.
The remainder of the collection consists of financial and legal files containing sales inventories and receipts, price lists, bills, loan agreements, and documents pertaining to the estate of Giorgio Spaventa, as well as photographic materials consisting of prints, negatives, slides and color transparencies of artwork.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Corcoran Gallery of Art; De Kooning, Willem, 1904-; De Niro, Robert, 1922-1993; Denver Art Museum ##naf; Dickinson, Eleanor,, 1931-; Diebenkorn, Richard, 1922-; Fogg Art Museum; Harris, Paul, 1925-; Kerkam, Earl, 1891-1965; Kline, Franz, 1910-1962; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Montana Historical Society.; Oberlin College.; Olitski, Jules, 1922-2007; Resnick, Milton, 1917-2004; Smithsonian Institution; Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; Spaventa, George, 1918-; University of Arizona ##naf; Worcester Art Museum; Yale University; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State)-- New York; Art, Modern -- 20th century; Photographs
- Elinor Poindexter Desk Files, 1947-1969; Series 1; 10 Folders Box 1
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by original file name.
  Scope and Contents note
  The Elinor Poindexter desk files contain clippings, press releases, Elinor’s biography, an index of articles about artists, savings bank documents, notes and personal files, legal documents, invoices, and miscellaneous correspondence.
  - Artists, Personal Advances, Past History, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artists' Publications Index, 1947-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gallery Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Invoices, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Legal, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes, Useful for Gallery, 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publicity, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Resume, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Savings Bank, 1959; 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1955-1971; Series 2; 1.8 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Arranged chronologically per original order.
  Correspondence chronicles the gallery’s relationships with different artists, including artists who exhibited there, as well as artists who they took an interest in. The series also includes correspondence between the Poindexter Gallery and other art galleries, museums, and colleges and universities. Notable correspondents include Worcester Art Museum, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Solomon Guggenheim Museum, Denver Art Museum, Yale University, Oberlin College, University of Arizona, the Fogg Art Museum at Harvard University, Smithsonian Institution, and the Montana Historical Association.
  - Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11-26)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 27-52)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 53-78)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1-25)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 26-51)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 52-77)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 78-96)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Form Letters, undated (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Letter Fragments, undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
- Artists’ Files, 1931-1983; Series 3; 2.4 Linear feet Box 2-5
  Arranged alphabetically by surname.
  The artists’ files represent the bulk of the records and are files that were created by the Poindexter Gallery in order to keep track of artists whose work they exhibited and whose work they were interested in. Among those represented in the series are the artists Richard Diebenkorn, William de Kooning, Giorgio Spaventa, Robert De Niro, Earl Kerkam, Franz Kline, Milton Resnick, Eleanor Dickinson, Paul Harris, Jules Olitski. Materials included in the artists’ files are correspondence, photographs of artwork, sales records, exhibition files, and printed materials. Due to the nature of the material as reference files, some of the artists’ files predate and postdate the dates that Poindexter Gallery was open.
  - Annesley, David, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Condon, Rudolph, Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Condon, Rudolph, Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Condon, Rudolph, Sketches, undated (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Condon, Rudolph, Writings and Printed Material, circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Davis, Gene, Biographical Information, circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Davis, Gene, Exhibit Brochures, circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Davis, Gene, Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Davis, Gene, Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - de Kooning, William, 1946-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - De Niro, Robert, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dickinson, Eleanor, 1966-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1963-1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1963-1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, Biographical Information, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, Lithographic Documentation Sheet, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1970 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1964-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, Photographs and Reproductions, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, Printed Material, 1964-1999 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Harris, Paul, 1966-1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Harris, Paul, Correspondence, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Harris, Paul, Catalogs and Clippings, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Harris, Paul, Correspondence, 1958-1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Harris, Paul, Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Harris, Paul, Photographs and Negatives of Works, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Hopkins, Bud, Biographical Information, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Hopkins, Budd, Exhibit Brochures, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hopkins, Budd, Magazine and Newspaper Articles, 1962-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Kerkam, Earl, 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Kerkam, Earl, Exhibit Brochures, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kerkam, Earl, Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1931-1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Kerkam, Earl, Photographs of Work, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Kline, Franz, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Levin, Kim, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Levin, Kim, Photography of Work, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - McNeil, George, Biographical Information, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - McNeil, George, Newspaper Clippings, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - McNeil, George, Photographs of Work, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Natkin, Robert, Biographical Information, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Natkin, Robert, Exhibit Brochures, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Natkin, Robert, Photographs and Slide, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Nankin, Robert, 1960-1968 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Natkin, Robert, Magazine and Newspaper Reviews, 1962-1969 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Olitski, Jules, Biography and Catalogs, circa 1964 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Olitski, Jules, Clippings, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Olitski, Jules, Correspondence, 1961-1972 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Olitski, Jules, Inventories and Price List, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Pring, Gwytha, circa 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Pring, Gwytha, Photography of Works, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Resnick, Milton, 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Shtainmets, Leon, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Slowinski, Ronald, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Soffer, Sasson, Biographical Information, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Soffer, Sasson, Exhibit Brochures, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Soffer, Sasson, Photographs of Work, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Spaventa, Giorgio, Biography, Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Speyer, Nora, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Suro, Dario, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Weeks, James, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Wilke, Ulfert, 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Woelffer, Emerson, 1958-1974 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Wonner, Paul, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Wonner, Paul, Biographical Information, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Wonner, Paul, Exhibit Brochures, 1958-1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Wonner, Paul, Exhibit Guestbook, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Wonner, Paul, Photographs of Work, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Yektai, Manoucher, 1961-1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Other Artists, Biographical Information, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Work, 1955, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Exhibit Brochures, 1962-1969 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Financial and Legal Files, 1955-1985; Series 4; 1 Linear feet Box 5-6
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title and thereunder chronologically.
  Financial and legal files document sales made by the gallery as well as day-to-day fiscal and legal matters. Materials include invoices, price lists, sales receipts, bills, inventories, and loan agreements. Also included are court papers regarding a claim brought against the gallery by the estate of Giorgio Spaventa after his death in 1978.
  - Bills, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Bills, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Bills, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Bills, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Bills, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Bills, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Bills, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Gallery Bills, Receipts, Invoices, etc., 1955-1961 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Inventories, Price Lists, 1955-1971 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Inventories, Price Lists, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Loans, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Loans, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Loans, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Loans, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Loans, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Loans, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Loans, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Loans, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Loans, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Loans, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Loans, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Loans, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Poindexter Gallery Business Papers, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Spaventa Estate Material, circa 1960s-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
- Photographic Materials, 1933-1977; Series 5; 1.4 Linear feet Box 6-7
  Arranged alphabetically by artist’s surname.
  Photographic materials consist of prints, developed negatives, color transparencies and slides of artwork by artists who were represented by Poindexter Gallery or in whom the gallery took an interest. Among the artists heavily represented are Alfred Puhn, Nell Blaine, Richard Diebenkorn, Steven Sloman, and Manchouer Yekati. Photographic materials pertaining to artwork also appear in the artists’ files.
  - Blaine, Nell, 1957-1971 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Blaine, Nell, 1965-1974 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bogart, Richard, 1968-1969, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dickinson, Eleanor, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1955-1975 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1961-1969 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, Negatives, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, Negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Gechtoff, Sonia, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Hall, Joellen, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Harris, Paul, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Herbert, James, 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Hitchens, Ivan, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Kerkam, Earl, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Klavun, Betty, circa 1971 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Natkin, Robert, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Sazegar, Morteza, 1964-1977 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Sloman, Steven, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sloman, Steven, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Snow, Michael, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Somberg, Herman, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Spaventa, Giorgio, circa 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Weeks, James, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Wonner, Paul, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Yektai, Manchouer, 1958-1964 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  - Yektai, Manchouer, Negatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Artwork, 1933-1963 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Artwork, 1955-1964 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Artwork, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Puhn, Alfred Photographs, circa 1950 (Box OV 1, Folder 1)